Guide to the Luther Bradish Papers 1801-1863, 1963 MS 71
New-York Historical Society
- Correspondence, Legal, Political documents (2 of 3 Folders), 1836 April-1836 December (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  April-December 1836 is divided into two folders and cover a variety of topics including: the Chenango Canal, circulars describing acts passed by the New York State Assembly (Folder 1), Whig Convention in Utica (Folder 1), suspicions around bank abuses (Folder 2), and contemporary politics.
  These folders also contain correspondence from Elkanah Watson (Folder 1) and Francis Granger (Folder 1).
- Correspondence, Legal, Political documents (7 Folders), 1837 (Box 6, Folder 3-9)
  1837 is divided into seven folders and covers a variety of subjects including: the Hudson and Berkshire Rail Road Company (Folder 3), Chenango Canal (Folder 4, 5), the General Banking Law (Folder 3), investigation of bank abuses (Folder 4, 5, 6, 7, 9), contemporary politics, creation of canals/railroads/aqueducts, Ogdenburgh-Champlain railroad (Folder 5), Great Northern Railroad (Folder 6), circulars relating to New York Assembly activities, and letters of endorsements for political candidates.
  These folders also contain correspondence with Frederic de Peyster (Folder 4) William Henry Harrison (Folder 4), Gouverneur Kemble (Folder 3), William Bouck (Folder 5), William B. Rochester (Folder 5), Henry J. Sedgwick (Folder 7).
- Correspondence, Political circulars (9 Folders), 1838 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
  1838 is divided into nine folders covering many subjects such as: the 1838 New York gubernatorial election (Folder 6, 8, 9), Luther Bradish's election as Lieutenant Governor (Folder 4, 5, 7), Bradish's answers to questions posed by abolitionists (Folder 4, 6, 7, 8), the Ogdensburg-Lake Champlain Railroad (Folder 1, 2, 4, 8), Moira, general Banking Law (Folder 2), Abolition Society (Folder 6), Erie Canal (Folder 2, 8), and letters of endorsement for public office.
  These folders also contain correspondence from John Quincy Adams (Folder 1), Gouverneur Kemble (Folder 1), Francis Granger (Folder 1, 4, 7), Thurlow Weed (Folder 1, 7), Nathaniel P Tallmadge (Folder 4), Gerrit Smith (Folder 3, 4, 7), William H. Seward (Folder 4, 7), Henry Bell Van Rensselaer (Folder 7), Elkanah Watson (Folder 7), Charles Bradish (Folder 2, 5), Henry Clay (Folder 2), Edward Sanford (Folder 6) and Jonathan Bradish (Folder 9).
  In his correspondence with Bradish, John Quincy Adams forwards him a petition from the citizens of New York. Some of the Gerrit Smith and Thurlow Weed letters discuss abolition, whilst Nathaniel Tallmadge discusses Bradish's run for the Lieutenant Governor of New York seat.
- Correspondence, Political circulars (3 of 7 Folders), 1839 January-1839 June (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
  January-June 1839 is divided into three folders covering several subjects including: the New York and Erie Railroad Company (Folder 10), the Hudson and Berkshire Railroad Company (Folder 10), abolition (Folder 10), the Canal Commission (Folder 10, 11), the Common School (Folder 11), and the Great Northern Railroad Bill (Folder 12).
  This folder also contains correspondence from Francis Granger (Folder 10), Daniel D. Barnard (Folder 10), Samuel B. Ruggles (Folder 10), Charles Bradish (Folder 10), General Stephen V. Rensselaer (Folder 11), John Bradish (Folder 12), and William Seward (Folder 12).
  The correspondence between Luther Bradish and Francis Granger discusses the DeWitt Clinton Memorial, whilst his correspondence with Samuel B. Ruggles discusses the New York and Erie Railroad Company.
- Correspondence, Political circulars (4 of 7 Folders), 1839 July-1839 December (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  July-December 1839 is divided into four folders covering several subjects including: the Hudson and Berkshire Railroad Company (Folder 1), the Ogdensburg-Lake Champlain Railroad (Folder 1), lecture invitations, the National Anti-Slavery Convention (Folder 2), and circulars asking Bradish to endorse candidates for various political offices.
  These folders also contain correspondence from Captain Matthew C. Perry (Folder 1), Henry Clay (Folder 1), and William H. Seward (Folder 1).
- Correspondence, Legal, Political documents (5 Folders), 1840 (Box 8, Folder 5-10)
  1840 is divided into five folders and in addition to general correspondence, there are documents relating to: Moira, the Ogdensburgh-Lake Champlain Rail Road (Folder 7), the New York College of Physicians and Surgeons (Folder 7, 10), Canal Board business (Folder 6, 7, 9), 1840 elections (Folder 8, 9, 10), the New York and Erie Railroad Company (Folder 8), and discussions of contemporary politics.
  There is also correspondence from Francis Granger (Folder 5), William H. Seward (Folder 5, 8), Gouveneur Kemble (Folder 5), Millard Fillmore (Folder 5), Benjamin F. Butler (Folder 8), and Martin Van Buren (Folder 7).
- Correspondence, Political documents (6 Folders), 1841 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  1841 is divided into six folders and covers many topics including: Canal Commissioners of the Canal Fund/Canal Board business (Folder 2, 3, 4, 6), Court of the Correction of Errors business (Folder 1, 2, 3, 4, 5), Political documents from Senate/Assembly (Folder 2), the Hudson-Delaware Railroad (Folder 2), abolition (Folder 1, 2, 6), Franklin County politics (Folder 3, 5), and discussion of Luther Bradish running for Governor of New York (1, 5, 6).
  Correspondence from Benjamin F. Butler (Folder 1), Daniel D. Barnard (Folder 1), George Gibbs (Folder 1), Philip Hone (Folder 1), Edward Delavan (Folder 1), and Jerome B. Holgate (Folder 4).
- Correspondence, Political documents (6 of 7 Folders), 1842 January-1842 September (Box 9, Folder 7-12)
  January-September 1842 is divided into six folders covering several subjects including: New York State Senate/Assembly Circulars (Folder 7, 9), discussion of the 1842 gubernatorial election (7, 9, 10, 11), Canal Commission/Canal Board business (Folder 7, 8, 9, 10), Erie Canal expansion (Folder 10), discussion of contemporary politics, Moira (Folder 7, 9, 10), the New York and Albany Railroad Company (Folder 8), and the New York and Erie Railroad (Folder 8, 10).
  These folders also contain correspondence from Edward Delavan (Folder 8), George Gibbs (Folder 8), Philip Hone (Folder 8), Nathaniel P. Tallmadge (Folder 8), and David Hudson (Folder 7).
  Edward Delavan's letters to Bradish mainly focus upon the New York Temperance Society. Philip Hone's correspondence focuses on the New York and Erie Railroad.
- Correspondence (1 of 7 Folders), 1842 October-1842 December (Box 10, Folder 1)
  The October-December 1842 folder covers several subjects including: the 1842 gubernatorial election, Moira, and discussions of contemporary politics.
  This folder also contains correspondence from Edward C. Delavan
- Correspondence, Circulars (2 Folders), 1843 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  1843 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: Luther Bradish's attempts to relocate to New York City, government related circulars (Folder 3), the New York State Agricultural Society, New York State Temperance Society (Folder 2), Moira (Folder 3), as well as discussion of the decline of the Whig party and rise of Locofocoism. (Folder 3)
  These folders also contain correspondence from Daniel D. Barnard (Folder 2), Edward Delavan (Folder 2), William Duer (Folder 2), and Daniel Dickinson (Folder 2).
- Correspondence, Circulars, 1844 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  1844 covers several subjects including: the Democratic Whig National Convention in Baltimore to support Henry Clay for President, abolition of slavery, the New York State Temperance Society, and New-York Historical Society.
  This folder also contains correspondence from Edward Delavan, George Folsom, and William Duer.
- Correspondence, Circulars (2 Folders), 1845 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  1845 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: the Ogdensburgh-Lake Champlain Railroad, Moira, the General Banking Law (Folder 1), the American Institute (Folder 2), the American Agricultural Association, and Trinity Church (Folder 2).
- Correspondence, Circulars (5 Folders), 1846 (Box 10, Folder 7-11)
  1846 is divided into five folders covering several subjects including: Trinity Church (Folder 7, 8, 9, 10), New York Senate/House of Assembly circulars (Folder 9, 10), Moira (Folder 9, 10), American Agricultural Society (Folder 8, 9, 10), the American Institute (9, 10, 11), the Franklin Academy (Folder 11), and the Episcopal Church (Folder 7, 9, 11).
  These folders also contain correspondence from Edward Delavan (Folder 8), Philip Hone (Folder 7), and Edward Sanford (Folder 9).
- Trinity Church, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  This folder contains papers relating to an attempt made by the Episcopalians of New York City in their endeavor to petition the New York Legislature to "alter the name of the corporation of Trinity church." (quoted from collection)
  Documents include: handwritten copies of the Act of 1814, the Charter of 1697, the Act of 1784, the Act of 1788 papers relating to Queen Anne's land grant permit, and a Remonstrance of Trinity Church.
- Correspondence, Circulars (4 Folders), 1847 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  1847 is divided into four folders covering several subjects including: the American Agricultural Society (Folder 2, 3, 4), New York Senate/House of Assembly circulars (Folder 2), Trinity Church (Folder 1, 2, 3), Moira (Folder 2), the Franklin Academy (Folder 2, 4), Common Schools (Folder 2), Normal Schools (Folder 2), the University of the City of New York (Folder 1, 3), the New-York Historical Society (Folder 4), and abolition (Folder 4).
  These folders also contain correspondence from William Curtis Noyes (Folder 1), Theodore Frelinghuysen (Folder 1), and Daniel Dickinson (Folder 1).
- Correspondence, Circulars (3 Folders), 1848 (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
  1848 is divided into three folders covering several subjects including: the Dewitt Clinton Monument Association, the University of the City of New York (Folder 6, 7), the Young Men's Henry Clay Association of the City of New York (Folder 6), controversy surrounding Brittain S. Woolley/Reverend Stephen H. Tying of St. George's Church (Folder 7), and various circulars relating to local New York politics.
  These folders also contain correspondence from Francis Granger (Folder 5), Philip Hone (Folder 5), and William Curtis Noyes (Folder 5).
- Correspondence, Circulars (2 Folders), 1849 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  1849 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: the DeWitt Clinton Memorial Monument Association, the opening of 11th St in New York City, the University of the City of New York, and government documents.
  These folders also contain correspondence from Francis Granger (Folder 8), William H. Seward (Folder 8), Theodore Frelinghuysen (Folder 8), Charles Butler (Folder 8), James William Beekman (Folder 8), and James Renwick (Folder 8).
  Both Francis Granger and James Renwick discuss the DeWitt Clinton Memorial Monument in their letters.
- B.S. Woolley Controversy, 1849 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  On December 1848, Brittain S. Woolley, "a parishioner of St. George's Church" in New York City was denied Communion by Reverand Stephen H. Tying of the same church. Tying denied Woolley communion because Woolley had published a "grossly false and anomolicious libel against [Tying], by a letter of advertisement...and accompanied said complaint with various documents." (information derived from collection)
  In response to Tying's actions, Woolley wrote a letter of complaint to the Standing Committee of the Diocese of New York.
  This folder contains various legal documents relating to the "B.S. Woolley Controversy" such as interrogations and testimonials.
- Correspondence, Circulars (2 Folders), 1850 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  1850 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: the Medical Societies and Medical Colleges Committee (Folder 1), letters of introduction, the University of the City of New York, the Northern Railroad (Folder 1), the Common School (Folder 1), the Free Academy (Folder 1), the Gibbs Family estate (Folder 1), Railway Convention (Folder 1), and the Industrial Exhibition in London (Folder 1).
  These folders also contain correspondence from James Beekman discussing the New-York Historical Society (Folder 2) and Charles Butler (Folder 2).
- Correspondence, Circulars, 1851 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  The 1851 folder covers several subjects including: the Free Academy, the American Bible Society, the New York-Erie Railroad, the Ogdenburgh-Lake Champlain Railroad, and the New-York Historical Society
  This folder also contain correspondence from: James W. Beekman, Wolcott Gibbs, and William Cullen Bryant.
- Correspondence, Circulars, 1852-1853 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  The 1852-1853 folder covers several subjects including: the American Bible Society, Whig politics, the National Convention at Baltimore, Locofocos, the Franklin Academy, Episcopalian business, and the Free Academy.
  This folders also contain correspondence from William B. Astor.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Newspaper Clippings, 1854 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  The 1854 folder covers several subjects including: the Astronomical Observatory in Central Park, the Nebraska Bill, honorary memberships to other historical societies, and the estate of John Malone.
- Correspondence, 1855 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  The 1855 folder covers several subjects including: Professor Louis Agassiz's "Contributions to the Natural History of the United States," the estate of John Mason, and discussions of contemporary politics.
- Luther Bradish and Rev. Corry Chambers, 1856-1859 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  This folder contains a collection of correspondence between Luther Bradish and Reverand Corry Chamber. Folder also contains a silk printing of one of Chamber's sermons.
- Correspondence, 1856 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  The 1856 folder covers several subjects including: potential merging of the Whig and American party, Central Park, the American Geographical and Statistical Society, the American Bible Society, the Mutual Life Insurance Company of New-York, Trinity Church, the New York Orphan Fund, and the Delaware-Hudson Canal Company.
  These folders also contain correspondence from: William Bradford Reed, Daniel D. Barnard, George Folsom, and Gerritt Smith.
  In his correspondence, Barnard discusses the potential merger of the Whig and American Party.
- Correspondence, 1857 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  The 1857 folder covers several subjects including: the New-York Historical Society, letters of introduction, the American Bible Society, and the King James Bible.
  This folder also contains correspondence from Reverend Henry Augustus Boardman.
- Correspondence, Circulars (2 Folders), 1858 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  1858 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: the Protestant Episcopal Society for the Promotion of Evangelical Knowledge, the will and estate of John Johns Esq., the American Bible Society, the Kane Monument Association (Folder 10), and many circulars from several organizations such as the American Oriental Society.
  These folders also contain correspondence from: George Folsom (Folder 10) and Charles Haynes Haswell (Folder 10).
- Correspondence, Circulars, 1859 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  The 1859 folder covers several subjects including: the Dudley Observatory, the American Bible Society, the Astronomical Observatory in Central Park, the Protestant Episcopal Society for the Promotion of Evangelical Knowledge, the New-York Historical Society, controversy surrounding Bishop Onderdunk, and a Fund for the Relief of Widows and Orphans of Deceased Clergymen.
  This folder also contains correspondence from William Aspinwall, Henry Jarvis Raymond, and Daniel D. Barnard.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Newspaper clippings, 1860 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  The 1860 folder covers several subjects including: the American Bible Society, the New-York Historical Society, the American Geographical and Statistical Society, Isaac Israel Hayes's polar expedition, the Pastoral Aid Society, the Prince of Wales's visit to New York, the New York and Erie Rail Road, and a comparison between slaveholding and non-slaveholding states.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Newspaper clippings, 1861 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  The 1861 folder covers several subjects including: preservation of the Union, slavery in the United States, Luther Bradish's declining health, the American Geographical and Statistical Society, the First Battle of Bull Run, the Young Men's Republican Union, the New-York Historical Society, and the Women's Central Relief Association.
  This folder also contain correspondence from Maunsell Bradhurst Field and Hamilton Fish.
- Correspondence, Circulars, 1862-1863 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  The 1862-1863 folder covers several subjects including: relief of families of New York volunteers, West Point, the New-York Historical Society and Central Park, the Pastoral Aid Society, as well as the American Bible Society.
  This folder also contains correspondence from Preston King.
- Death of Luther Bradish, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  This folder contains modern correspondence from the Rhode Island Historical Society and Trinity Church (Rhode Island) providing details about Luther Bradish's death and burial. There is also a modern death certificate for his first wife, Elizabeth Gibbs Bradish.
- Free Academy, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  This folder includes a draft speech delivered by Luther Bradish, circulars/pamphlets relating to the Franklin Academy, miscellaneous correspondence, and legal documents related to the Free Academy. (Related materials can be found in Box 12, Folder 3)
- Banks, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  This folder contains correspondence relating to the General Banking laws, bank reforms, and bank investigations. There are also studies of various banks in New York State and copies of acts passed by the New York legislature relating to banks. (Related materials can be found in Box 7, Folders 1-9)
- 11th Street and Churches, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  The documents in this folder focus upon the opening of 11th Street in New York City, between Broadway and Bowery. (For related documents see Box 10 Folder 5 and Box 11 Folders 2, 6, 9)
  This folder also contains documents focusing upon the Vestry of Grace Church. (For related documents see Box 10 Folder 10 and Box 11 Folder 3)
- Canal Commission Report, Undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  This folder contains several documents relating to various aspects of canal creation and the Canal Commission. The Chenango Canal features prominently in this folder. (For related materials, see Box 5 Folders 11, 14, 15 and Box 6 Folders 1, 2, 4, 5)
- Report of Mutual Life Insurance Company, Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  This folder contains part of a massive report relating to the Mutual Life Insurance Company.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Political documents (9 Folders), Undated (Box 14, Folder 6-14)
  These undated docments are divided into nine folders covering several subjects including, but not limited to: the Chenango Canal, 11th Street, children's education, the Delaware-Hudson Canal, the Ogdenburgh-Lake Champlain Railroad, Free Academy, Greek independence from Ottoman rule, and Moira.
  There are also various incomplete draft letters by Luther Bradish, miscellaneous memos, legal documents, sketches, and receipts. See oversized folder for additional content.
- Canals, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  This folder contains several documents relating to various aspects of canal creation. Some of the subjects discussed are: the Chenango Canal, Delaware and Hudson Canal Company, the Schuylkill Canal, Buffalo Canal and Black Rock Canal, as well as Lehigh Canal. There are also miscellanous and incomplete memos.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Political documents (7 Folders), Undated (Box 15, Folder 2-8)
  These undated documents are divided into seven folders covering several subjects including: Acts passed by the New York Legislature, the New York Agricultural Society, the American Agricultural Society, the Port Kent/Hopkinton road, maps of Moira, the Episcopal Church, the New York-Erie Railroad, the Chenango Canal, the London Exhibition, the Free Academy, the American Bible Society, the Hudson and Berkshire Railroad, the University of the City of New York, the American Geographical and Statistical Society, the Delaware-Hudson Canal Company, and Trinity Church.
  There are also various incomplete draft letters by Luther Bradish, miscellaneous memos, legal documents, sketches, and receipts.
- Metal Name Plate, Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  This folder contains a rectangular piece of leather with a "L Bradish" metal name plate in the center.
- Central Park Astronomical Observatory, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  The papers in this folder relate to the creation of an astronomical observatory in Central Park. Documents include circulars, reports, and the draft of an "act to incorporate the Observatory of the City of New York."
- Correspondence, Circulars, Maps, Political documents (9 Folders), Undated (Box 16, Folder 2-10)
  The undated documents found in this box are divided into nine folders covering several subjects including: Moira, the Free Academy, Trinity Church, the Pastoral Aid Society, the University of the City of New York, the American Agricultural Association, the DeWitt Clinton Memorial Association, Canal Board business, enlargement of the Erie Canal, Trinity Church, the Whig Convention, the New-York Historical Society, the estate of John Mason, the St. Regis Indian reservation, the Central Park Astronomical Observatory, the New York and Erie Railroad, Grace Church, the American Geographical and Statistical Society, banks, and the Delaware-Hudson Canal Company.
  There are also various incomplete draft letters by Luther Bradish, miscellaneous memos, legal documents, sketches, petitions, circulars, and receipts.
- Correspondence, Circulars, Sketches (4 Folders), Undated (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  The undated documents found in this box are divided into four folders covering several subjects including: a petition to create ferries between New York City and Brooklyn, bank investigations, the Chenango Canal, the Brush estate in Demerara, the Gibbs estate, Moira, Trinity Church, and the University of the City of New York.
- Invitations, Undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  This folder contains 113 invitations to Luther Bradish. These invitations were obtained by New-York Historical Society as a gift from George A. Zabriskie on October 20, 1939. Zabriskie later donated an additional 39 invitations to the collection on August 7, 1941.
- Business Stamps, Undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  This box contains two stamps. One stamp reads "L.B" and the second reads "Luther Bradish, Assistant Treasurer U.S., New York.
- Arabic document, Oversized, Undated (Folder OS-Medium)
  Undated illuminated Arabic document placed in oversized. Although undated, this document was likely obtained when Bradish was sent to negotiate a treaty with the Ottoman Empire.
- Menus, Oversized, Undated (Folder OS-Medium)
  A menu from Hotel de Londres (St. Petersburgh) and Menu Carte a Mange (Paris) was removed from Box 14 and placed into oversized.